Andrei Ruslantsev

Moscow, Russia, 108814 ($open\ to\ relocate$) | and reirus lantsev @gmail.com | https://www.linkedin.com/in/andreirus lantsev | https://github.com/arus lantsev | $Visa\ sponsorship\ required$

Summary

- **3+ years of experience** in machine learning (mostly using Python and pytorch)
- Launched product matcher from scratch twice in two different companies
- Experience in building reliable systems from scratch using existing infrastructure
- Currently I am a Senior data scientist in Aliexpress Russia

Skills

Languages: Python, Matlab, Maple, Swift, C++

Technologies: Machine learning, Neural networks,

Distributed Computing, MapReduce

Tools: pytorch, spark, sklearn, numpy, pandas,

Linux, Bash, gitlab, jira, maxcompute (pyodps),

LaTeX, Word, Powerpoint Source control: git, dvc Metodology: Scrum

Databases: Clickhouse, Postgresql, Hive, MySQL.

IDE: pycharm, jupyter, vscode.

Accomplishments:

- Launched product matcher from scratch with matching precision 95%
- Increased matching coverage by 20%
- Increased warehouse picking efficiency by 24%
- Mentored two trainees

Work Experience

Senior Data Scientist, Aliexpress Russia, Moscow, Russia.

Oct. 2020 — Present

Project: Knowledge engineering – product matcher

Accomplishments:

- Launched ML-based product matcher from scratch in 6 months with matching precision 95%
- In next 3 months increased coverage of the most valuable categories by 20% with matches
- In next 7 months doubled matcher recall for all categories
- Automated matching quality monitoring

Technologies: Python, pytorch, Clickhouse, Airflow, pyodps, Docker, MaxCompute

Lead Data Scientist, InTechControl, Moscow, Russia

Jun. 2019 - Present

A small startup developing software for finding defects on samples tomograms

- Developed software for automated search for defects on tomograms of carbon fibre reinforced detais
- Developed ML-based software, which fully-automatic creates 3D model of detail with defects from tomograms of detail
- Software provided 90% precision of defects search

Data Scientist, OZON.ru, Moscow, Russia.

Feb. 2019 — Oct. 2020

One of the top-3 biggest Russian marketplaces, 12000+ employees, Market capitalization 7.2+ billion \$

Project: Warehouse management system optimization

Accomplishments:

 Increased warehouse picking efficiency by 24% by developing a new order fulfillment algorithm using optimization methods

Project: Product matcher

Accomplishments:

- Launched ML-based product matcher from scratch in 1 year and reached required indicators
- Provided 30% coverage of goods, taking into account the main competitors
- Mentored two interns

• Lectured on machine learning to students

Technologies: Python, pytorch, Spark, Hive, Airflow, Clickhouse

Research officer, Institute of Machines Science, Moscow, Russia.

Aug. 2012 — Feb. 2019

Russian leading research institution in the field of machine science (mechanical engineering)

Project: Mechanics of composite materials

Accomplishments:

- Wrote and defended PhD thesis on time
- Developed analytical mathematical models for fiber reinforced plastics (deformation and fracture analysis, deformation under time-dependent loads)
- Organized and held international conferences "Deformation and Fracture of Composite Materials and Structures" in 2014, 2016 and 2018

Technologies: Python, Matlab, Maple, LaTeX, Word, PowerPoint

<u>Teaching assistant</u>, Bauman Moscow State Technical University, Moscow, Russia. Sep 2015 — Feb. 2019 Accomplishments:

- Developed a course approved at the department, which was taught 2 years to BMSTU students
- Two students defended their diploma projects with honors
- Designed tasks, homework and control software for automatic task checking on Mechanics of composite materials

Technologies: Matlab, LaTeX, Word, Powerpoint

<u>Laboratory assistant</u>, Bauman Moscow State Technical University, Moscow, Russia. **Sep 2010 — Jun. 2014** *Accomplishments*:

- Refurbished and recommissioned laboratory testing equipment, the rotary casting machine worked for 8 years without breakdowns after my recommissioning
- Developed a probabilistic model of particle redistribution during the rotary casting process of suspensions

Education

PhD degree in Solid Mechanics

2014 — 2018

Bauman Moscow State Technical University, Moscow, Russia

BMSTU is one of the best Russsian universities, which entered top-300 of QS World University Rating Departament of Aerospace composite materials

Research area – nonlinear and time-dependent deformation of carbon fibre reinforced plastics

Master's degree in Materials science and technology of materials

2012 - 2014

Bauman Moscow State Technical University, Moscow, Russia

Departament of Aerospace composite materials

GPA: 5.0/5.0

Research area – suspensions casting process simulation

Awarded President of Russian Federation scholarship in 2012-2013 and 2013-2014 for outstanding academic excellence

Awarded Club of the Imperial Technical School scholarship in 2013 and 2014

Bachelor's degree in Materials science and technology of new materials

2008 - 2012

Bauman Moscow State Technical University, Moscow, Russia

Departament of Aerospace composite materials

GPA: 4.9/5.0

Research area – suspensions casting process simulation